<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: raw idea | Bits and Pieces]]></title>
  <link href="http://DimaSavitsky.github.io/blog/categories/raw-idea/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://DimaSavitsky.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-16T18:32:54+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://DimaSavitsky.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dmitry]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Emotions-based action points for turn-based tactical games. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://DimaSavitsky.github.io/blog/2014/07/13/emotions-based-action-points-for-turn-based-tactical-games/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-13T23:01:46+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://DimaSavitsky.github.io/blog/2014/07/13/emotions-based-action-points-for-turn-based-tactical-games</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A lot of modern tabletop role-playing games have some kind of mechanic to describe player character&rsquo;s temper. Most importantly, to help fleshing it out. It helps players to have an initial idea of how to handle the narrative and the relations with other in-story entities(NPC). Additionally, such a system often has some substantial mechanical benefits and constraints.</p>

<p>The following post is an inconsistent ramble about a mechanical idea I was pondering about for some time: <em>In a turn-based tactical game featuring a squad of characters to use character&rsquo;s emotional state expressed in numerical format as action points.</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So, a ramble:</p>

<p>Disposition: A squad of characters travels on a global map, occasionally breaking into a turn-based combat.</p>

<h3>First example</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s assume that it is possible to influence character&rsquo;s (both protagonists and antagonists) emotional state before the fight. For example, through dialogue.</p>

<p>In this simplest example there is two possible emotions tracked by the mechanic: <strong>calm</strong> and <strong>enraged</strong>. Each turn each character gets some points representing one or the other state of mind to spend on actions, the probability depending on his stats.</p>

<p>We have a team of two protagonists: Barbarian and Cleric.</p>

<p>Barbarian is an angry fighter-type, whose MO is smashing things. Among his possible actions, all being direct attacks, most need the player to pay with <strong>enraged</strong> points.</p>

<p>Cleric, on the other hand, needs to stay <strong>calm</strong> to pray to his god for divine interventions, but he can occasionally bash someone with a mace if he is <strong>enraged</strong>.</p>

<p>Both characters get some emotional points(<em>marbles</em>) they can spend on actions per turn. Barbarian&rsquo;s probability of getting an <strong>enraged</strong> marble rather than <strong>calm</strong> is 6 to 1, for example, the Cleric&rsquo;s is 1 to 3.</p>

<p>Being a poorly built character, Barbarian suffers if he occasionally gets a random <strong>calm</strong> point, because he has no use for it. What the player can do in this situation is: try to develop a character into having a use for them (communing with ancestor spirits mid-fight), or try to pump the character before the fights(&ldquo;they spoke badly about your ancestors&rdquo;) to improve the probability of him being <strong>enraged</strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
